howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is michelle bauwens
michelle is the founder and vision
coordinator of the p2p
foundation and works in collaboration
with a global group of researchers
in the exploration of peer production
governance
and property there's an amazing
collection of content at
p2pfoundation.net
and there's a very interesting daily
blog which they put out
blog.pdpfoundation.net
it's also well worth following
michelle's twitter feed
all kinds of interesting things there
this is part two
of a previous discussion that michelle
and i had back a ways it was
ep 63 on the jim rutt show you can
search
ep63 jim rutcho and you'll find it
and we'll as we were doing then basing a
fair amount of our conversation
on the book peer-to-peer the commons
manifesto written by michelle
and two co-authors uh vasilis castakis
and alexis maybe you can say their names
for me michelle you can say your name is
better than i
think names are not always that easy but
uh i think it's uh
alex pasaritis but i could be wrong
anyway pretty close while it's not
necessary to hear the previous episode
it would be helpful or particular if you
find this conversation interesting go
back in here
basically about the first half of the
book before we jump in though i am going
to ask michelle to
review two main topics which are
critical to understanding
what we're going to be talking about and
those two topics
are what is peer-to-peer in its simplest
level
and then another concept which goes
through all of michelle's work
is the idea of the commons so i would
ask michelle to give us a little review
about what he means when he says
the comments so let's start with what is
peer-to-peer
right well i think a lot of people in
your audience will know that
it was used in the technology field
about 15-20 years ago when
you know we we had this new
configuration where any computer
could talk to any computer without going
through a server or
any centralized entity and so what i'm
saying is this is also social
relationship
so we have now technologies which allow
peers
to permissionlessly connect with each
other
you know communicate with each other
organize things with each other
and also uh you know actually
produce value together and distribute
value together so it's much more than
just communication technology it's a way
to
you know create alternative value
circuits that
may or may not be market oriented and so
to understand the historical
significance you know imagine a little
village
uh ten thousand years ago you know
everybody everybody is your uncle or
your nephew or
your niece and so if you have any
conflict
you basically talk it out you know as
long as it's inside
the village you you can you know
peacefully arrange
uh any conflict uh but then as we got
bigger as humanity we
you know we we created big organization
and it's just impractical and too
expensive to do
everything you know anybody everybody
talking to everybody so we basically
invented a hierarchy
you know once you have centralized
hierarchy then it's it's very difficult
to do peer-to-peer because you're
competing you know with with
armies and other countries and and and
so that was really
uh something that i think was very
determining
in our human history but i think today
we are
able technologically and socially to
create
vast projects like you know linux the
free software
operating system or you know arduino
open design electronics
uh and we combine thousands and
thousands of people who are not
necessarily working
in a hierarchical relationship to each
other so
you know to be a bit provocative i call
this a peak hierarchy
and so the idea that distributed
networks can be as strong
as centralized entities you know it's an
it's an open
uh dynamic but i think this is very
interesting and then of course how both
try to adapt to each other
and and create hybrid uh configurations
uh the second point the comments is the
idea
of shared resources so basically
you know you can allocate resources
through the gift
which is uh you know in complex tribal
civilizations you
you know one family one clan one village
gives something
and that creates uh a duty of
reciprocity and that's how you basically
create social relationships and keep the
peace
then we got into you know wars of
conquest and it becomes redistribution
so basically the empire you know you get
overrun
and you get lots of advantages but of
course you have to have disobedience
and paid tribute and the third one
is the market and the fourth one is the
commons this is a totally different
logic
so anybody can contribute to a shared
resource like the linux free software
system
and everybody can use it and
this can be done also in the physical
space uh you know there's a tenfold
increase in urban commons
in cities so 10 times more in just 10
years time
but you can do you know all kinds of
things
using that dynamic and so you have to
put it next to the state which is about
redistribution
and next to the market which is you know
about equal value exchange
this is about building things
collectively which have an advantage for
all the participants
who are contributing so this is the time
of the re-emergence of the commons
because
as we are overusing
resources on the planet historically
what has happened after
such extractive periods is that humanity
uses the commons as a kind of healing
mechanism
because pooling and mutualizing
resources
is absolutely the best way to bring down
the human footprint there's no
nothing else even beats it uh closely
uh so that's why the comments today are
such important then you put the two
together
you know peer-to-peer dynamics creating
comments together that's that's
the era we're in in in my view
well very good that was a good crisp
discussion of those two key concepts
we'll come back to lots of times so
let's jump into
chapter three of the book and talk about
peer-to-peer and the new
socio-technological
frameworks you say in theory
the internet should provide a capacity
for many-to-many communications
using all other forms of media and a
capacity for self-organization
that is a result of permissionless
communication and the capacity
to create distribute value in new ways
i.e self-organization could be put to
use in the sphere of production
tell us what you mean by that what are
the benefits because those are seemingly
all positive attributes and then maybe
we'll talk a little bit about maybe some
of the negatives that seem to have
emerged from this ecosystem
right absolutely so you know there's
nothing in the world that is a pure good
so it's always
you know two sides of the coin so i'm
very happy to discuss the negative side
but you know just as like 10 years ago
people were exaggerating the positive
sides
people are now exaggerating the negative
size and they're forgetting
all the benefits that we got with it
right so it's
it's a question of finding the right
balance in within those two polarities
so um i don't know if you remember this
but
maybe 10 15 years ago uh pekka himanan
wrote a book the hacker
and it was kind of updating that book by
max weber called the spirit of
capitalism
you know which described the emergence
of capitalist values capitalist ethics
after the reformation and you know he
makes the link between
how the religious reformation at the
same time
uh meant that you know markets became
something positive
right so pekka himmenon describes this
uh
emerging field of free software and he
notices a complete change
in mentality and so basically the two
values are
passion and freedom so we now have
social technical systems which allow
people
to join them by choice so they are open
collaborative systems
and so that freedom creates passion
so the fact that you can actually choose
your activity the ones that you love the
most that
that you find the most meaningful
creates at the same time this
very huge motivational extra
and you know think about to to make it a
very simple
example you have encyclopedia britannica
which you know i used to use an
absolutely excellent resource but then
you have the wikipedia where
you know 100 percent of the people there
are there because they want to be there
right
um and so no matter how much money you
have how big you are how expert you are
it's very hard for uh
that kind of entity to compete with this
kind of open network
and so what will happen is that you know
usually
one or more individuals say we want to
do this like
we need an alternative operating system
uh you know to uh not having not having
to use microsoft for example or
we want direct access to organic food in
our neighborhood without you know going
to the
big store and paying 30 percent more
whatever the goal is we you we now
basically have the freedom to broadcast
these projects and then
people would adhere to it and they will
do so with a substantial amount of
enthusiasm
and so most of the time these these
projects start with passion
but of course you can't eat passion so
the second step is usually how can we
make a living
and continue doing this because we
really like and love to do this
right so around these
open productive communities you'll find
an entrepreneurial coalition and i call
it sometimes the enter
donario coalition because of course
ideally
around the commons you want a vibrant
market system that actually benefits the
commoners and also
takes good care of the you know the web
of life the natural resources that are
used in that project
so you around this productive
community you try to create a generative
economy an ethical economy
and so that's step two step three is you
have to manage the infrastructure
and so what you do there is you create
neutral
associations for benefit associations
which enable and empower
the collaboration to occur so typically
for example the wikimedia foundation
will not order you know people to write
the articles but they will
have editors that have the power to say
no
and that's very important because that
defends the integrity of the system
so it's not a command hierarchy but you
still have a control hierarchy
and you know the free software and
associated
technologies you know you know is one
sixth of gdp already since 2011
so this is a substantial part already of
the
u.s economy and and the global economy
now i want to explain one important
dynamic
once you have a system where some people
get paid and others don't get paid
you have a question do i want to do
things for free
and see only a few people benefit from
our common work
and so that creates a whole kind of
dynamic
where these communities are going to try
to do things differently to have more
equity
and this is sometimes called
pre-distribution
so imagine you create a membrane around
your productive community
you you know you get market income maybe
you get subsidies or whatever you get
from the outside
but internally you can redistribute the
value
in a different way and that's called
contributory accounting and there's
hundreds of them
you know hundreds of examples that i
have in my p2p accounting section
uh of my wiki so you
will try to create new types of
relationships with the entrepreneurs
for example we are big fans of something
called reciprocity licensing
and the basic idea here is
knowledge is free knowledge can be
shared but
if you want to use it commercially you
know you have to become a member of the
association
or you know some kind of reciprocity
arrangement
uh which uh you know it's kind of a
promise of reciprocity basically
this is less important in free software
because you know everybody can use it
it's
it's it requires fairly
relatively low capital but if you want
to do
you know some project with machines and
buildings and actually produce something
you you may want some protection from
purely predatory
uh you know companies so just take the
open source
but don't reciprocate so what we're
seeing is
you know first we had a free software
and open design communities then we had
the urban commons coming on in 2008
with a tenfold increase uh and now we
see the first premises
of distributed manufacturing and we call
it cosmo local because
everything that slides is global and
shared
and everything that's heavy is local
and pos and potentially cooperative
so just to give you one example of this
this is called the multi-factory system
it's a coalition of 120
crafts factories in europe
so these are usually people who do
materials so you know
converting plastic or working with wood
or iron
or steel or 3d printing and they kind of
you know look for cheap
abandoned factories in the you know in
the ports of the cities and stuff
but they do this cooperatively they use
open source methods and they have what
they call the invisible factory
which is the place where they work
together you know
independent of the the place where they
are working so
they have their own commons if you like
where they're building this collective
experience and knowledge
for their whole network so this is a
typical example of what we call
cosmo local production and
you know this is very very important
because we spend three times more
transporting stuff than making stuff
right
so if you can produce at the place of
need
on demand using distributed
manufacturing this should have a
substantial effect
on the human footprint and if you
pull your resources you know you you
mutualize
parts of your provisioning systems
then you get enormous benefits because
you know we we calculated it
uh in a report called the thermodynamics
of peer production and we
we looked at the agriculture and it was
about 80
so you know produce as much food but
with 80 less uh matter and energy usage
yeah that's very important it's one of
my own personal passions
is the local agriculture movement but
unfortunately as it turns
out the economics are still hard to get
to work right
so long as we don't have a strong carbon
tax
because you know all that moving of food
from california to the east coast or
even worse a salmon caught in alaska
sent to
china to be processed and then sent back
to the united states
gets a free ride by not paying the full
cost
of the transportation and my own
calculations say
if you put an honest carbon tax say 100
us dollars or 100 euros per ton of
carbon equivalent
suddenly local agriculture can out
compete the industrial agricultural
machine but until then it's going to be
hard especially
in you know places that are optimized
like the united states
very very efficient industrial
agricultural systems hard to out compete
it on price
absolutely and maybe i can say something
about this because this is very
important so
you know we have a value regime we have
decided in the 18th century
that wealth is created through
extraction so you know you need scarce
commodities in order to be able to price
them
and that's how you realize the surplus
and so typically anything that's
regenerative or regenerative and
anything that creates abundance becomes
cheap or free right so that you you have
a fundamental contradiction in our
system where
an organic farmer who improves his soil
every year will get punished
because the farmer who destroys the soil
every year
will get much more subsidized and and
all kinds of stuff
uh and so that's fundamental so as we if
we don't change to a contributory
value regime the things that we need to
change in the world
you know are not going to work very well
you know unless
you're going me to willing to be to to
extremes and i
i was recently looking at the bruderhof
communities which
i'm quite impressed with i you know it's
not the kind of life that i would
lead because you you know you have to
promise obedience and and pretty much
um you know forget about your personal
development it's you know it's a
religious
uh uh system but i don't know if you
ever seen them i mean they're
you know they they're
very productive they're and they have
everything they need
and so what they've done what they've
done is you know some kind of radical
mutualization like the monasteries did
in the middle ages and you know they've
grown to 3 000 people it's uh
you know it's it's worth looking at and
i don't know if you can confirm this but
i learned that the
amish you know also very collaborative
in their community
actually have the most productive
agriculture in the u.s i
find it hard to believe but i've read it
in two or three articles
and so it's probably worth looking at
whether that's true or not
yeah it's interesting the bruderhofs i
actually drive right
by one of their industrial facilities on
the way to visit my daughter
someday i'm going to have to stop in and
visit up in pennsylvania
in the united states with respect to the
mennonites and amish
there's a lot to be learned there but i
would also caution you
that they are exceedingly industrial
in their agricultural processes heavy
users of pesticides and fertilizer
oh really yeah they'll use up land and
then move on
and so yes they are amazingly productive
and their farms are
very prosperous but i would say that
they
are not at all on board at least most of
them with regenerative agricultural and
permacultural techniques
and so there's a lot to learn there but
i would say that they're by no means the
perfect model they're one of the
one of the models that i've been
studying lately the mennonites
and also the israeli kibbutz now the
israeli kibbutz
is another extremely interesting model
uh
which i would suggest might actually be
more appropriate
in many ways than the mennonites though
i do advocate
the mennonite style of local collective
decision-making about technology
right in the mennonite world the
communities are organized into something
kind of like
parishes in regular protestant or
catholic religion but they're quite
small 25 to 50 families
and the technological decisions about
whether we should adopt a technology or
not are made at that level
and often after years of debate and
they'll come to different conclusions
people think oh yeah the amish they all
do this they all do that no they don't
they vary at this
local level for instance some will allow
electricity in the barn for the milking
machines for the cow
and refrigeration but no electricity in
the house then some will say no
electricity at all
and so i think there's a lot to be
learned there but i would caution that
their
agricultural practices tend to be
more industrial than you would think
because they're tightly coupled to the
monetary system
but the other thing that's worth
learning from them is they have an
alternative form of finance
they essentially have collective banking
where if you're a mennonite or amish and
you want to start a business and many of
them get into
businesses like furniture building or
construction or
small factories they don't go to banks
generally speaking
they will go to their community and they
have a form of collective capital with
return built into it
so they can avoid the exploits from the
commercial banking sector
and whatever interest or implied
interest comes back
is kept within the communities i think
there's a lot to learn there yeah
absolutely
another distinction i'd like to make you
call it the light and the heavy i think
in our game b world one of the
distinctions we make which is
very similar and maps almost on to light
and heavy but not quite
is the distinction between rivalries and
non-rivalrous
non-rivalrous means things that can be
replicated very inexpensively
and that can be digital like you know an
mp3 file
obviously costs very little to replicate
but it also can include drugs you know
many many drugs now can be manufactured
for
one penny one cent per pill and yet they
may still
charge you know 20 a pill and so things
that can be duplicated
at a very small fraction of their
competitive market equilibrium value
really ought to be made in as large a
possible
volume as people want should not be
constrained by
intellectual property at least to the
point where it's you serious
well rival risk goods like a ham
sandwich either you eat it or i eat it
right
it may not be heavy but it's rivalrous
and so there's a very different dynamic
there and there's always going to be
issues about who gets what and so i
also suggest laying that framework on
top of thinking through
alternative systems and we should
encourage the widest possible use of
non-rivalrous goods
and put our attention to reforming how
we think about the
cooperative signaling related to the
creation and distribution of the
rivalrous goods
that's exactly how i started my p2p work
20 years ago with the kind of conclusion
that
our society treats immaterial goods as
if they were scarce
so we basically do everything we can to
make
cooperation difficult to intellectual
property and all kinds of
uh rules so you know we we're creating
artificial scarcity in the immaterial
world in a world of light you know what
we
what we said and we treat
material things as if they were infinite
so we we don't take into account
that you know there's only so much
copper and so much oil and so much
of a resource in the ground uh and so
you know it's it's the opposite of what
we should be doing right we should take
into account
that we do live in a relatively finite
world
and that we uh should make it difficult
for people
to solve problems together because
that's the issue
that the the system that we have is
creating all these kinds of systemic
crises
but then it creates really heavy
barriers about how to solve them
and you know i used to work for bp a
long time ago in the early 90s
which is at the time that they were
buying up all these solar
companies and uh electric cars
and basically destroyed them you know
that was like physically destroyed
electric cars
back in the day because they they didn't
want this to compete
uh you know with what they had
and that's only possible because of co
because of copyright and intellectual
property
you know if you had open designs then
other people could have made
these uh electric cars so we lost in my
view we lost 30 years because of this
yep and it's a fundamental problem and
whatever comes out on the other side of
the crisis we're headed to i certainly
hope that people will remember that we
should
make that which is easily reproducible
without being burdensome upon the earth
reproducible and as you implied you know
to my mind the number one mission
of the human race in the 21st century is
to learn to live within
the boundaries of what the earth can
continuously produce
and not just for our own good but also
for the other species that we share the
earth with
and so those two things together strike
me as you know the first two pillars
of creating this new world now we talked
about
the cool things that can be done on the
internet and sure enough there are a lot
of you know i was
involved with building the internet and
the pre-internet i actually started
working
at the very first consumer online
service back in 1980
a company called the source in fact i
designed one of the earliest email
systems and i designed one of the
earliest forum systems
and was also a product manager for one
of the first precursors to what we might
call today social media
wasn't exactly the same but it was close
enough so anyway i've been watching this
stuff and participating in it since the
very beginning
and i will say we all thought we were
doing the lord's work right we thought
that
we would be building tools that would
make democracy better that would make
everything fairer many things we just
talked about and indeed
those things are happening and it's as
you point out it's important
to focus on the positives too but
unfortunately
maybe i've been a little late today i've
come to realize that there are some
serious negatives we have to think about
about this emerging
internet world in fact i did quite a
long podcast yesterday
with daniel schmoktenberger on
sensemaking on the internet and how the
internet as it's
evolved and not by design i will say
there is no conspiracy for this to
happen
it's the emergent result of capitalistic
signals essentially
we've ended up with a set of very strong
network attractors amongst the
quasi-monopoly platforms like facebook
google twitter
instagram etc and these things have
taken
essentially combined very sophisticated
cognitive science and cognitive
neuroscience with machine
learning to create a system where we're
actually being
controlled in ways we do not understand
and
i tend not to be a believer in
conspiracy theories and whack-a-doodle
like that
but i think in this case it is true that
we have developed an emergent world
where
what should have been these tools of
liberation have instead been
i think what you called cognitive
capitalism where our behaviors
you know our information and our data
are essentially turned back around
against us for the purpose of selling us
ads and the ads are sold for the purpose
of you know turning us into something
that we are not
and so while there are gigantic
potentials
and accomplishments for the internet i
do believe it's now time to turn
our attention to the problems with it in
fact i like to call out here
a great movie that just came out
yesterday
and i watched it last night it's called
the social dilemma
it's on netflix and it is
tristan harris of humane tech place he
plays the narrator in it
and it's an incredibly powerful
examination
of how these platforms are controlling
us in ways that we don't understand i
strongly recommend
people watch that and the other and she
appears in the film
is called surveillance capitalism by
sushana
zuboff who focuses mostly on google
but also a bit on facebook and how these
tools that should be
you know core to human emancipation have
you know again not through malicious
intent but through
these mega companies responding to the
signals of
capitalism particularly as they
transition to an advertising model
no longer our friends and in fact are
destroying our ability for collective
sense making
and may well be driving our whole
society insane
well i i'm very close to that analysis
because
you know i've been a curator for almost
15 years now i mean longer because i you
know
i've been a librarian since uh you know
my first job in 1981
um but you know as a curator
you know the simple fact that you want
to
you know be pluralistic in your sources
has become extraordinarily difficult um
you know so we had this
idea of the filter bubble some years ago
which you know these algorithms kind of
tend to present to you
what confirms your interests and your
opinions
but now we've come to weaponizing of
this is which is that
you know as communities are fragmenting
what happens
is that i actually don't want any other
information
they they actively try to protect
themselves
uh from anything that disturbs the
righteousness or whatever it is that
determines
their being together in a community and
that's really really painful i'm
i've lost a lot of joy you know doing
this kind of work in the last
two years because of this yeah it's a
very real thing in fact the film the
social dilemma
focuses on that you know we think
intuitively
that everybody and his historically this
was sort of true had more or less
similar sources of information and we
could
assume that at least people had some
agreement about the facts if not about
what should be done about them
but because of these filter bubbles and
these algorithms which
select things that outrage us which
press the dopamine buttons in our brains
it's now the fact that people have very
different flows of information they're
not similar
at all right no no but you know even if
you do a search
in uh in google uh on i'll do it on my
computer you'll do it on yours
we we even that we won't find the same
things anymore
yeah they think of a very good example
on climate change if you type in climate
change
the auto continuations i.e the suggested
searches you do
are radically different depending on
where you live
so if you're in texas it'll say you type
in
climate change and some of the suggested
continuations
is a hoax you know is nothing etc if you
do it in new york city it will say
is a existential risk to humanity
and it's interesting nobody at google
made those decisions
these were machine learning based
extractions from patterns of what they
saw
which as you say creates a filter bubble
does not present
objective view of reality but rather
reinforces a set of prejudices
so that new york and texas now have
radically different views about climate
change even though there's only one set
of objective facts
which neither side sees in a pure form
right so maybe one thing we we can do
and this is you know what i'm trying to
do with the p2p foundation
so this is called object-oriented
relationality
you know it's one of the branches of
maybe sociology i'm not sure
but the basic idea is that you know what
is the commons about
it's a shared object that you want to
make
and so in this case what you're doing is
that you're congregating but you're
congregating to build something
right and you you so you look for
commonality
and you organize around the commonality
which is the love of that object be it
free software
or it's a bit similar to
you know i was reading an article in
jacobin magazine today about
you know how unions back in the day were
able to create
kind of unity between the workers of
different races and
and and uh you know other differences
because they were all kind of
had this common identity you know we
workers we will struggle together
it's good for us if we all fight
together around you know
uh some common priorities
uh as opposed to the fragmentation that
we that we
have right now um and you're probably
familiar with the work of uh
is it peter lindbergh with you know
culture 2.0
this mapping of 30 different mimetic
tribes
that you know all have their own logic
all have their own convictions
and are not seeing and reading any
anymore the same
things this is uh so i see commenting as
a potential
also strategy to overcome at least some
of that fragmentation
by focusing on you know this kind of
common
priority that we could have if we build
things together
yeah i think that's really what we have
to work on but we have to be realistic
about the fact that these monopoly
attractors armed with
machine learning are not attempting to
do that and we have to
find ways to either overcome it and one
of the things for instance i find
facebook for instance for all of its
evils if you stay out of the
broad public facebook and spend your
time in private groups
many of the dynamics go away right they
don't run very many ads in the private
groups
private groups have their own algorithms
which are objective actually and they're
not
driven by the zuckerberg algorithm etc
so one can
adapt one's usage to not be quite as
sucked into these attractors the other
one i'd recommend to everybody
turn the goddamn notifications off on
your devices
don't let them pop at you because they
are trying to get your attention
turn all the notifications off the other
two things i personally do which i'd
recommend is i take a
six-month break from social media every
year that's really good i should do that
as well
yeah in fact at the end of month two of
this year's break from july till the end
of december
and it's amazingly liberating and the
other is even when i am
on social media and this has to do with
other things too like
email is once a week i take a day's
break and have a cyber sabbath typically
on sunday
where i don't touch any device at all
except my kindle i have
like the good mennonites i say well
kindles are all right kindles are like a
book right
and so again these are habits that we
can get into
to free us at least a bit from cognitive
capitalism
let's go on now to a model that you have
in the book
which is about how we can use this
network infrastructure and other things
then you basically create a two by two
good
management consultant fashion uh
centralized
versus global and you know for-profit
versus for benefit and you have four
different boxes and maybe talk about
that a little bit
right so so let's take
each quadrant by you know in turn and so
the ones that we
were just discussing is basically the
idea of
centralized peer-to-peer infrastructures
with a for-profit goal so the facebooks
the googles they still
do allow you know peer-to-peer
connectivity
but everything except the front end
is actually centralized right it's
centralized property
it's centralized governance they own
your data et cetera et cetera and and so
we know where that is going and that
that's not good news then the other one
is distributed but for profit
and he here's what i'm thinking is the
bitcoin world the blockchain world
the crypto world because if you look for
example a bitcoin is very clearly
designed
you know as a commodity currency to go
up in value
so in other words it is designed to make
a profit
and the ideology behind it is a
libertarian
ideology which you know sees every
individual as separate
from each other and then you can engage
in market transactions
what they don't see though is that any
competition for scarce resource
creates oligarchy
you know whether you're competing for
land or you're competing for money
it doesn't really matter in any
iterative game
uh for scarce resource one people
true luck and cleverness and hard work
whatever the reason is
we'll end up having more resources than
the other and then for the next
iterative game you're stronger and
you're concentrating resources
and not only that but actually that's
you know they're really designed to do
that right they have
oligarchic protocols like proof of stake
and proof of work which give
more to people already have so that's
that's a group apart which claims to be
peer-to-peer but actually
you know creates oligarchic systems in
in their effects
and then you have on the other side two
for benefit
models and one is the local
distributed for benefit models and
that's really what's happening in the
urban commons
you know there were 50 urban commons in
the city of gentile 2008
and 500 in 2016.
so there is this explosion of local
initiatives you know faced with stated
market failure
people are really mutualizing a lot of
of their provisioning system
and so what we saw in gen for example
was that
every provisioning system had already a
commons-based alternative
whether it was a community land trust uh
housing co-ops and co-living
arrangements
for housing whether it is uh you know
shared
transport uh but not uber but you know
associations and co-ops that do similar
things but
way better uh whether it is
uh you know shared the food like uh
collective purchasing uh you know with
farmers
for organic food so the whole field is
is filled with those local bioregional
regional effects and maybe you know two
three percent of population is
engaged already in these alternatives
and
you know we've seen it with the maker uh
movement uh during covet
you know in the early phases of covet
the uh there was you know the hardware
wasn't there
you know the ventilators the masks
everything was missing
and you saw the extraordinary you know
mobilization of maker spaces
to do this kind of cosmo local
production and that brings us to the
fourth quadrant which is the global
quadrant
and this is about the global open design
communities
um you know i'm looking forward to the
days when we can have planetary guilds
uh that protect workers that work on
these global systems
um so it's uh i look forward to what i
call
protocol co-ops uh so to give you an
example of this
you know there's this coalition called
c40 uh
of uh cities in the world which want to
do climate change and you know and for
example one of the things they would do
is looking at regulations to rein in
uber and airbnb right but that's just a
negative regulation what i want to see
is fair bmb and muni right in other
words
multi-stakeholder you know mutualized
facilities that are
you know managed by the people who
[Music]
produce them
and and use them and so
one of the things i've been proposing to
the cities that i work for
is okay you create a global open design
depository for let's say share mobility
you make a deal with the coalition of
cities you know like in the middle ages
the ancient league for example uh
you create you know ethical finance
impact finance coalition and you create
uh solidarity coming cooperative economy
social entrepreneurship
and with all of those things you can
create
you know based on common protocols local
adaptations so that you can neutralize
transportation
much faster than any other you know way
could
could achieve so you see you have those
four alternatives
it all depends how you design the cyber
physical infrastructure
and ideally this is kind of my vision of
the future
you know i want an integration of the
best of the best so we have
in open source and the commons we learn
how to do mutual coordination
right stigma energy the the capacity to
see the signals
of all the others working in the same on
the same project
so that you can coordinate and adapt in
real time
to what others are doing market pricing
works very well
you know for to allocate really scarce
resources
and so we can work on generative markets
and finally you know what we call
orchestrated planning which is the role
of the state
but we can also imagine global
governance institutions that
for example the global thresholds
an allocations council which is proposed
by r3.o reporting 3.0 which is
actually holding its conference right
now
and the idea here that they propose is
to have a council
of scientists monitoring the
availability
of resources matter and energy
globally and then come to some some type
of agreement
about you know what is the fair
distribution of those
allocation rights uh and that would then
be reflected in accounting systems right
so that you everywhere you would know
how to use
resources without going over the planet
boundary so it's kind of like
the donut economy idea of cate wayworth
but integrated in in one
accounting system and this is why
despite my critiques
i still am very interested in the
blockchain world because
what they're doing is going from an
internet of communication to an internet
of transaction
right the distributed ledgers can
allow us to create at scale
uh open ecosystems to produce something
together on a world scale both locally
and globally
and to adapt to each other and to be
able to respect the planetary boundaries
so that's that's kind of what i've been
working on recently
yeah i think those are all important
things first thing i want to talk about
is public shared ledgers
you know you didn't quite say it but
i'll say it
i don't like bitcoin i think bitcoin is
bad it's a replication of bad patterns
from the past it was explicitly based on
gold
and as you point out it makes the rich
richer it's got lots of other problems
it's
consuming electricity at a ridiculous
level etc
so while it was a very important proof
of principle
and in fact when i read the bitcoin
paper when satoshi put it out i read it
i don't know a few months after he
published it i said
i slapped myself in the head so this is
brilliant why didn't i think of
that it's not that difficult actually
but it was
a brilliant innovation but the bitcoin
implementation i would say
much of the ethereum work though not all
of it is in the wrong direction as you
say it's
reinforcing kind of a libertarian hyper
individualist dog
dog epic on the other hand blockchain
can be used
in much more positive ways too and you
know i pointed before to the holochain
project we've had arthur brock on the
show a couple of times to talk about
hollywood which is not a blockchain i
mean you know it's a distributed ledger
without being
based on the blockchain oh
yeah it's a different style it's in the
same general family but it's
you know very very different and it's
really designed for what i would call
mostly
good purposes and then there's other
kind of things which are more
purely written on the blockchain such as
the ocean protocol
which is a very clever way for people to
own and share their data
etc that's also we're looking at so yeah
this is an area
that's a big innovation and i hope we'll
eventually produce
a major win for society and a tool kit
that we can add to work with
but not all examples are good we have to
curate
you know the tools that we use from this
domain yeah
that's so that's why i talk in in this
uh
latest report about value sensitive
design
right so if you're libertarian you
a commodity currency if you're common
oriented you think about the mutual
credit
currency um if you're
a libertarian you think about smart
contracts
if you're a commoner you think about
ostrom contracts and you can make a list
of about a dozen things
that you know how you would differently
design a distributed ledger system
if you are inspired by common values
versus libertarian values
so i think it's very important for
people to understand that
technology is not just neutral
it's you know it's an active terrain of
struggle
or construction if you like that better
but
the way your values are are reflected in
the way you design that's
those systems which then will be
influencing everybody else who's using
them
and it's not a simple thing you know you
look at the internet right first is the
non-commissioned officers uh of the us
army
that stress that it has to be
peer-to-peer to survive
nuclear war it's taken over by
scientists
then it's taken over after 93 by the
public with the web
with the web and then the companies take
over
you know with with introducing client
server
and then this the surveillance state you
know uh
wants to control everything and so it's
it's one technology but it has different
layers of design principles which are
actually not that much in harmony with
each other
yeah could you send me the link to that
i want to make sure we put that on the
episode page
yeah we'll do that sounds absolutely
central
you know a design ethos is what can help
technology liberate us not enslave us i
would say
you know again we get deep into these
issues so we're kind of moving along
here in time i'm gonna
move from this topic which we could talk
about probably for two hours
and move to your chapter four i
personally found this extremely
interesting and that was p2p in the
structure of world history in the
various
modes of production and organization of
production and exchange which have
happened over time
i do want to make sure we have plenty of
time for governance which is
something dear to my heart but let's
spend at least a little bit of time
on your take on the p2p and the
structure of world history
right well so when i when i started
with the p2p foundation um in 2000
you know two-ish i started
with discovering the relational grammar
of alan page fisk
and he's the one and i i we talked about
it about
40 minutes ago who distinguished between
commoning
working together on a common on a common
project that is a
shared resource the gift economy
he calls it equality matching where you
give something
that creates an inequality and a desire
to give back
the market uh and then what he calls
authority ranking which is about
redistribution and what
and then i discovered the second author
uh which is called kojim karatani
and he wrote an amazing book called
the structure of world history and he
says
that you know these these things that
on page fisky mentions are actually also
active in history but in different modes
of combinations
and there's always a dominant mode so
human history actually starts with a
common so you have
very small tribal groups that usually
are nomadic
you know when the hunters come back with
uh
let's say a deer it's not for the
hunters it's for the family
and there is a protocol for distribution
of the pieces
and actually usually the hunter he gets
released because he has already the
prestige
of the hunt but so you know the idea
that it's
for everyone at the same time in a
particular group that's really the
very first modality of human exchange
uh as we get more complex bigger
uh you know bigger villages and tribal
federations
that's where the gift economy comes in
equality matching
because that's kind of social obligation
that allows you to pacify uh
you know tribal warfare because as long
as you can move along in small bands you
know you don't have to go to war you
just move out
the world is big enough for everyone but
once you have
uh tribal federations you know the the
gift economy
skips in then comes the what he calls
authority ranking so
once a tribe decides you know to invade
another tribe
well you can have a gift economy right
because it's a form of domination
so you have to justify your domination
and basically it's going to say
we protect you we bring advantages in
exchange for tribute and obedience
and so according to your rank in the
hierarchy you get
more than another person in lower rank
of the hierarchy
and finally market pricing and so
another way to put it
is that capitalism is a combination of
capital state and nation right
capital drives everything the
accumulation of capital is the name of
the game
the state creates a framework in which
this can happen
and is also the place for keeping a
balance uh you know at the meta level
of society so the state has a double
role if you like
and the nation is is the community and
they emerge at the same time and
it's one system capital state nation
and uh what i'm saying is that
if you look at the micro foundations of
open source
and peer production you might actually
deduce a new
combination which is values produced not
in the market alone
but through all the contributions in
civil society
so the value regime changes and becomes
common-centric
the commoners need to make a livelihood
and create livelihood organizations
through a generative economy which
includes
you know market dynamics
and then you have these for benefit
associations like the linux foundation
and drupal association which you know
manage the infrastructure of cooperation
and like a common good institution like
the states
so it's kind of transformation of the
state so my political program if you
like
jim is to transform civil society
the market and the nation all at the
same time
a modest little project very much and so
my first book was actually called
you know changing the world but of
course i'm not saying
i'm going to change what i'm going to
i'm saying that you know
all peers should be changing the world
and so i i would like to add something
to that so i've been
very interested lately in what are
called wave pulse theories and the idea
is that
societies move from one polarity to
another
uh extractive periods of competition
usually tends to an overuse and a
collapse
and that creates a pulse towards going
to the other
polarity which is a period of
regeneration
and healing of society and so you look
at society and you see this con
continuous polarity changing
and remarkably the commons is the
healing agent
in regenerative periods
there's a fantastic book by mark
whitaker
which is called ecological revolutions
and the actual religions
and he basically shows us in the past
and he looks at china 12th century japan
15th century and europe in the
8th century and he sees the same thing
so
the system is in crisis like the fall of
the roman empire and what happens
mutualization at a big scale to heal the
society
and so this was of course going on in
regionally limited periods within
regional planetary boundaries
but now we have arrived at global
planetary boundaries and that tells me
that we have to achieve this kind of
next transformation
and it it we have to escape the pendulum
we have to escape the pulse
because we now have nowhere else to go
then keep the planet
in a steady state right so that's kind
of what you know a lot of ecological
uh thing is we tell you is that we need
some kind of degrowth period where
our amount of usage of matter energy has
to go down to a certain degree
part of what we save can go to solving
the
huge global problems that we have with
you know people are homeless and still
hungry
and many places but the aim is to arrive
at the steady state
system where humanity knows what to use
of its bio in our capacity and so you
could say that we have to move from
a capital labor compact which was the
basis of the welfare state
to a compact between humanity and nature
to recognition of our place
in web of life and towards interspecies
community you know collaboration
in maintaining uh you know the health of
our planet
so that's kind of the challenge and i
believe that peer-to-peer dynamics and
the commons are a crucial part of that
transformation
very good i mean a couple comments one
it strikes me that as you said we have
to avoid it this time without the pulse
right because we have too far to fall
we've built
a very high stack of infrastructure and
systems and should we
fall we're going to fall a very long way
and
we have used the power of this game a
hierarchy as we would call it
to allow population to grow to 8 billion
and if the hierarchy collapses
or if the underlying structures collapse
too rapidly
many of those 8 billion people will die
i'm afraid
second i think this is very important is
when people talk about d
growth i think that that can be
perceived as overly simplistic
now you did caveat it and this is
absolutely critical that we have to
degrow
our imposition on the regenerative
powers of mother nature
and so you know we have to stop fossil
fuel use by
2050 probably we have to get better at
recycling
metals and things but there's still lots
of room to grow
quote unquote in ways that aren't
material i call that growth into the
microcosm
rather than growth into the macrocosm
you know for instance
better poetry or a new song
is growth in some sense right in fact my
friend tyson yonkoporta who've had on
the show three times
he's of an australian indigenous people
background
he says that in their culture they make
a big distinction between
increase and growth so for instance
if the crops you grow get better on the
same land without any material inputs
but you just take good care of the land
that's
increase while if you open up new land
and destroy the native habitat that's
growth
and increase is better than growth and
so i would
you know ask people have some nuance
about this that
degrowthing doesn't mean things can't
get better but they
require a different concept yeah
absolutely so one of the concepts that
we use is
you know sustainable well-being which is
uh you know how can you actually
increase the well-being of people
within the framework of sustainability
of planetary boundaries
and you know i fully agree with you i
mean that's you know i will not use the
growth in my public communications
because
you know when people are struggling to
survive you're not gonna tell them that
they have to be even poorer
that's that's not what this is about
this is about
you know stopping waste uh
it's and it's about directing life
towards the growth of the things that
make us really happy
so i just see the growth of the at the
material usage as a kind of objective
necessity
but it's absolutely not a way to
communicate politically
about these these issues and that's why
i think commoning is also
important because you know when you do
meaningful work in a group
that's a huge boost to your to your
personal happiness right it's it's a
it's an expression of your being and so
there's a lot of things we can do that
go in that direction
that make people a lot happier than you
know the mere
accumulation of material stuff that you
actually don't use
that much yep absolutely and again
we both know that an awful lot of
capital could be shared
and you know things like tool libraries
or
transportation as a service run the
right way
oh by the way i want to revisit that
even though we talked about it in the
last show
you talked about you know a better uber
there actually
are a few examples like in the city of
austin texas
about 50 of the market for rideshare is
by
a driver-owned co-op which is kind of
interesting
but to your other point it would be
really nice if somebody documented how
they did it
and you know what their legal structures
were how they dealt with regulation etc
and make that available as a package for
other people around the world to be able
to take those seeds and plant them
elsewhere
yeah that's what i call a protocol
cooperative you know because the
protocols are publicly available and so
people
can take them and adapt them to you know
other
other contexts interesting yep
all right let me introduce another
concept here which is relatively new
i think quite new comes from one of my
collaborators a guy named jordan hall
and he has five or six youtube videos
on the concept that he calls sivium
c-i-v-i-u-m
so youtube civilian jordan hall will
bring it up
and it's informed by the work of jeffrey
west and louise
bettencourt who are both affiliated with
the santa fe institute
and their work showed in a very
convincing fashion
that cities are quite unlike biology
biology is sublinear when an elephant
you compare an elephant to a mouse
an elephant might be ten thousand times
heavier but it does not use ten thousand
times as much energy or
water it goes down at a sublinear
scaling at the three-fourths power as it
turned out and so maybe an elephant uses
200 times the energy of a mouse even
though it's 10 000 times bigger
but the opposite is true for cities as
cities
get bigger they are super scalar in a
whole lot of dimensions
some positive and some negative for
instance we know
patents are generated at a higher rate
per capita
in larger cities economic wages are
higher
in larger cities per capita but also
crime is higher and disease is higher
etc and so the super linearity
has some very interesting consequences
particularly and it's one of the reasons
why we're developing these
mega cities all around the world with
populations of 20 million or more and
particularly in the third world
many of them are fairly horrible places
in terms of quality of life and impact
on
the local environment at least and of
course in the west
the super cities become dominant in the
economy in their region
are sucking resources in from all over
causing people around the world
to degrade the environment and come up
against the limits
and i would say at this point beyond the
limits of growth
and further this is i think the new
addition that jordan adds to
this analysis is that cities make people
crazy
you know you look at the rate of which
people go to psychotherapists you know
you look at
and you just think about the kind of
life you have to live in a big city you
know where you're
looking down at your feet in the subway
not talking to your neighbor you don't
even know who your neighbor is in the
apartment building
you deal with everything has been
reduced to the transactions of the
market or the government
there is no face-to-face community most
people who move to the cities
don't bring their whole extended family
with them so they're social isolates
and so jordan has proposed taking some
of things you've talked about
the ability of the nets that we start to
recreate society from the bottom up
in small groups a few hundred people
in the mostly rural areas that create
extraordinarily high quality of life
to the degree that's reasonable that
they be self-contained with respect to
things like power and water depending on
where they're located they may be able
to be self-sufficient with respect to
food too but they also should be open to
the wider society to trade
for things that they can't do for
instance they're not going to make their
own computer chips
anytime soon or airplanes or other
things but
and this is the key so they can
contribute to the global
shall we say increase they need to be
coupled to the wider world and to each
other
so that they can have the good parts of
superlinearity of large
groups of humans interacting and yet
still provide
a very humane and low impact quality of
life
and i find this synthesis completely
interesting and engaging
and have been starting to dig into it in
some detail
i'd love to get your thoughts on the
idea that we can capture the good that
comes from large groups of humans
interacting
and yet build humane and low-impact ways
of living
at the same time well it sounds a bit
like you know our idea of cosmo local
uh organization right which uh so i'm
i look i mean i have opened the tabs
i've never actually
taken the time yet to look at the you
know the whole
series but it sounds like something that
is totally
interesting i have some friends in
france who
have calculated that if we want 100
organic food
we need 12 percent of the people back in
the countryside
what we also have to know is that you
know italy
spain uh portugal
france have you know hundreds and
hundreds of empty villages
you know the villages are actually there
nobody wants to live there anymore
but you know if we can create a non-isil
a non-isolated cultural life
i think we could have this type of you
know global global villages
that are both local but you know also
intensely connected
with the intellectual and cultural life
of the world and i i think basically
with internet there is no reason
anymore to make that huge distinction
between the countryside and the city
and i have a friend from the global
villages
project it's called give g-i-v-e
which is doing a virtual university of
the villages
because you know if you're in a village
it's
hard to get a good professor to come by
and give a lecture
so they mutualize and they invite you
know the best professors in austria
to teach uh people in the villages i i
think those kinds of things go in the
same direction of what jordan is
trying to propose so i'm definitely
interested in learning more about it
yeah i think it's i would point people
to it is something that i would suggest
is highly congruent with your ideas and
then combines them with the
west betancourt findings about
superlinearity of cities to produce what
is a
pretty compelling way to think about
ways forward
we're getting late here in time again
damn it we have so much interesting
things to talk about
and so little time let's move on to the
payoff chapter five
a commons transition strategy
what do we need to do yes
i can't exactly recall what i wrote
in that fifth chapter and i must say
i've been a bit
you know in a more doubtful mode because
uh i think what we see happening is that
the
social collapse is you know speeding up
much faster than the
ecological collapse and so you know the
political situation is becoming hugely
complicated
but so basically what i'm advocating is
so new model and i focus around the idea
of partner state
and public commons cooperation protocols
right
so moving away from this idea of a
top-down
state to an idea of a partnering
state and that can you know happen at
all levels including global governance
institutions
but let me give you an example i don't
know if we did that last time but you
know you have the bologna regulation
for the care and regeneration of the
urban commons
it creates a lab it allows all
citizens in the city to say i want to
care for this as a commons
so abandoned buildings you know
parks that are not kept well uh even
cleaning the the river
sides and there's many many things that
can be done
and so the there's a process of
negotiation validation
then a commons accord is signed
and the city then becomes the
coordinator of the support
and they have this system called the
quintuple helix system
which is the city the chamber of
commerce
the research organizations and the
official ngos and all these four
combined together to help number five
which are the
common-centric uh social
innovators and i think this is a great
model and it has been
copied by 250
other italian cities and it has
mobilized one million
italians in working for the commons
at their local urban scale so i think
this is a
you know something that actually needs
to be done everywhere because
if you recall what the maker movement
was doing with covid
you know they were very very fast at
producing those things but then
the hospitals were afraid to accept
their their material because of all
kinds of legal
and liability issues that they you know
they didn't want to
cross those lines and that is a huge
waste
of uh you know potential in in value
so i think this is very important that
we need to
you know step away from the the binary
state
or market and move at least to a
triarchy
where you know what's the best
combination of
economic activities from the market
orchestrated planning and regulation
from
the partner state and you know and
support
mechanisms and then of course the
autonomous activity of the commoners
so that that for me is very important
that we start moving in that
simultaneous transformation
of civil society the market and the
state function
using those concepts of public commons
cooperation protocols and
i don't know if i wrote anything else
there you had some other things but i
think you hit the big picture
you know things i wonder about is trying
to do all three at once
is that feasible i would say our game b
movement at the present time
is focused on just doing proofs of
principle at the local scale
and including some of jordan's civilian
ideas on how the local communities
would have protocols for interacting
with themselves in the wider world
in a way to have a super scalar ability
to
have increase if not growth and leave
the state reforms till later though as
you point out the current
meta crisis may not let us do that i
guess our perspective is that the
politics is so broken
particularly in the united states but
increasingly across the west
that it may not be worth participating
in
partisan politics at this time yes i
i fully agree it's difficult but i i i
think we still need to
you know to to have an integrated
holistic approach
and you know don't forget not everybody
has to do everything right so so
you know i i fully agree that you know
if you're engaged in doing a local
project you know your energy is going to
making that work
uh but i think at some point you do have
to
you know create a relationship with the
public authority and
you know at a local level it might not
be as bad as at the national level right
all these games that national level
politicians can play
because they can put up one group
against another
uh when you're at the local level you
know if there's a riot you're you're
there's nowhere else to go
right so there's i think a strong
motive for local politicians to behave
uh substantially differently than at the
national scale
yeah absolutely and we do say that yeah
and i i'm advocating the creation of
assemblies of the commons and chamber of
the commons
and commons transition coalition so the
first one assembly
is where all the people who are engaged
in creating and protecting commons can
you know find each other
uh and you know arrive at the consensus
of what needs to be happening in terms
of regulation
and you know and then we have a chamber
of commerce which is all the
the livelihood organizations uh you know
how can we make healthy businesses
around the commons
uh and then the co the commons
transition coalition is the people who
have more of a political consciousness
and and wants to work directly on those
regulations
i frankly think we do need to do
everything
at the same time and give you an example
for example the
economy for the common good is a
proposal
um to create a common good accounting
system with 17 classes of impact which
already exists
they've been doing this for 10 years and
when you have an investment policy
you can start saying well we're only
going to invest and support
those industries
that have a positive impact right
so you lower your taxes in higher
subsidies
for generative businesses and you lower
it for
degrading practices and so
you keep the companies you keep the ceos
but you change the entire
incentive system around them right
so we need to find those things which
can accelerate
the change so my view of companies is is
a bit
you know like can't live with them and
can't live without them so
they have often a predatory dna
but we're not going to get rid of them
within 10 years which is what we need to
do
for you know rapid transition so we need
to find ways to work with them
and guide them and push them with a
framework that still allows them
maximum of freedom and autonomy but kind
of guided by those regenerative
principles
now this work on the chamber and the
assemblies is that actually happening
now
because i sense a strong interest in all
the various groups
that are working that are more or less
pointed in the same direction though
with different emphasis and different
theory
starting to communicate more in sharing
practices it's something i've been
calling the big
change coalition and i'd love to see
something like that happen
it is happening at the others you know
not big enough scale but for example
in france you have about at least 15 now
you know they're called fabric of the
commons or you know they have different
names
but they're essentially a place where
commoners get together
there's also more and more food
transition councils energy transition
councils
like you know i come originally from
brussels and there's a regional
transition coalition
there is even in france already a
website you know politics of the commons
which has prepared
solutions that can be given to
politicians during
elect electoral periods when they're
looking at you know their planning and
their agenda
so what to do with habitat what to do
with transport
so those things exist already like you
know if you want to do
commoning of housing you need a
community land trust approach
you need cooperative housing and you
need co-housing right
those are three different models that
cover the ground
the houses and the the functioning of
the houses
internally so these things exist but
they need to be
interconnected so we suffer from
fragmentation that's for sure
yeah i would say i would go even a step
further and say that while the commoners
and commenting is a great approach and
has a lot of richness to it there are
other approaches
that are i think pointed in the same
direction
you know for instance the regenerative
ecology movement
it's similar but not the same and
another one that i've become quite
interested in lately
is political metamodernism the hansi
frynack
and our own game b i think fits in that
category and i know a
half a dozen maybe a dozen more that are
each taking a somewhat different
approach
but we can think of it as having a
coherent pluralism
there's a small group of things we agree
upon and there's a broader group of
things we agree to disagree about
and i think an association at that level
could be really
useful right at this time yeah it's
about measuring it's about
meshing perspectives you know each
perspective brings something to the
table
that others didn't see but it also
because of its filter
doesn't see other things right and so
the more perspective you can mesh
together
the more you shine light on the on the
problems and
and the objects um and so
i wouldn't put ourselves in a situation
where
we say you know all in the comments is
the answer or only
meta modernism is the answer but kind of
you know
interconnect interweave uh those
different approaches
and then like discuss solutions and and
enrich the solutions be
through this intermeshing of an
encounter
i think that that would be uh you know a
big way forward
oh that's i'm glad for you to hear that
because i've been talking to a number of
people about this and they all say
they're ready to do it
and i may call some people together to
try to get this rolling sometime early
next
year and you will certainly be high on
my list of people
i will be happy to participate ah very
good
well i think we're getting close to the
end of our time here
any final thoughts on the way forward
and particularly in the context
of the suddenly pretty hot meta crisis
we seem to be finding ourselves in
yeah that's a it's a real problem
because i think we discussed it
in private uh you know before we opened
the recording
um or maybe we discussed in the
beginning i can't remember sorry
but the way social media are
weaponizing difference is
extraordinarily disruptive
um you know i'm a curator i'm a
pluralistic curator i've done that all
my life
and i've never been under so much
pressure to limit
my sources and on both sides there's
extraordinary
exaggeration where uh you know when i
hear somebody on the right saying bernie
sanders is radical leftist you know i
i'm laughing because you know it's
scandinavia which is like
totally normal here in europe there's
nothing radical about it
uh you know it's already a 100 years old
right and the same way on the left
you know like you know even the slight
descent is not called outright
and and most people don't even know what
it means so this kind of inflation
of demonization uh is a huge huge
problem
so i i i'm very much for projects like
you know protopia lab
or new discourses or or others that
the store are you know these these
places where people can learn to talk to
each other
again because that's that's very very
important if we
you know if you have multiple
perspectives and you know as a curator i
do this every day
i look something up and i look first at
the factual
basis you know is this likely to be true
or not and and
i can double check and triple check
certain things
but i also try to understand the
narrative frame right
so how do these people come to these
conclusions
and you know it's almost never out of
evil
it's almost always out of fear and
so what i'm trying to say here is that
we have to be you know really learn to
talk to each other
and to accept you know divergent
perspectives and to find ways to
transcend those uh those differences to
a certain degree
what you can do in the comments is you
know put some difference on the brackets
right you say
we are here to do free software you are
libertarian
i'm a social democrat well that's not a
problem in this context
because we both want to have good free
software you see what i mean
so creating constructive
projects that allow us to put
certain things under brackets i mean
even people who believe in you know q
anom
can be very nice and friendly people
and you know i wouldn't agree with them
but as human beings i can have a
conversation
a respectful conversation about
you know don't we need a good
neighborhood don't we need to improve
the schools don't you know what i mean
so that's kind of i think what needs to
happen
yeah i call that concept alignment
beyond agreement
that we can be in alignment with people
on
some big picture things you know we may
need to make human life more humane
right very few people i think would
disagree with that
though we may disagree about the
techniques to get there and let's talk
about our disagreements and
as a librarian you know that one of the
ways to help
make sense of disagreements is try to
get to the facts first and that's what's
really breaking down in our society is
that
people have their own facts which is
extremely dangerous when people
think that they have facts that are not
compatible there's only one reality
people
one set of facts is true and both sides
need to back off of their tribalism
unfortunately some people question that
very you know very basic
fact yeah those are goddamn
postmodernism which
at least the flattened form i got no use
for there are some interesting things in
post-modernism
but that one that all points of view are
equal is just ridiculous right
or which doctor is not the same as johns
hopkins medical school sorry
astronomy is not the same as astrology
well we need some
some uh you know common methodologies to
educate
differences right so that's that's
that has to be there otherwise we will
never make any progress on these issues
well i think at that point we're going
to wrap up here michelle this has been
again another
remarkable conversation which i think
will help the world actually
and you know i think we painted at least
a reasonably hopeful
road forward yes thank you so much jim i
enjoyed the
both our conversations and thank you so
much for you know bringing all this
material uh
to the people
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com